welcome to the saturday sangha
cultivating wisdom with john vervicky if
you're joining us
for the first time there's a lot that's
happened we've done an entire
meditation and contemplation course
drawing from the eastern traditions of
buddhism and taoism
so to catch up with that check
for links in the description go and do
lesson one
do one or two lessons every week but you
can continue meeting with us
you might also want to take a look at
lesson one of
the wisdom of hypatia course that we're
now on
after we finished with the examination
the deep study of the
wisdom cultivation we could gather from
the eastern traditions we're now seeing
what we can gather from the western
wisdom traditions
using brian mcclendon's book the wisdom
of hypatia
drawing wisdom inducing wisdom from
epicureanism stoicism
and neoplatonism we've done epicureanism
we're finishing up stoicism we're going
to move into
neoplatonism so as always what we're
going to do first is we're going to
begin
with a set and we'll start with some
chanting
and then we will go into the silent set
we'll come out of it
uh we'll switch cameras i'll go to the
whiteboard and we'll have some dharma
um we're going to wrap up with a with
looking at wasari's
reconstruction of a stoic form of
meditation
i think it's actually a form of
meditation and contemplation it's
analogous in some ways to prajna
but we'll get into that right now get
yourself in your posture
set your phones on do not disturb and we
will begin together when i say begin
begin
[Music]
one
begin your silence set
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communicates
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay i'm going to move over to the white
board so we can begin their dharma talk
so we are finishing up with uh stoicism
and i want to remind you
of where we've been and i want to give
you a bit of the pedagogical structure
that we've come through so here's
epicureanism
epic for short and here's stoicism
and we're heading towards neoplatonism
and so we can think of these as
overlapping
and we can think of the core practices
within epicureanism
we can think of like inside here is the
pleasure diet
we talked about
structuring your pleasures and then we
talked about
disciplining the imagination
practices for stopping the imagination
from terrifying us
and then there's a savoring practice
and then in here there's an overlapping
practice which is the philosophical
fellowship practice
the philosophical contemplative
companionship
but i've started calling it the
philosophical fellowship practice
ran lav emailed me he's fine with that
um he and i are going to talk so that's
very cool of course in stoicism
uh we have self-examination
cultivation of virtue we have active
open-mindedness
we have the view from above we have
objective seeing
we have the pre-meditation now we're
going to do a practice
that is going to be uh that bridges
between overlaps with
neoplatonism and this is what bizarre
calls
stoic meditation
i think a better way of putting it
because it involves both meditative and
contemplative
i want to call this practice and i think
it's going to
be much more helpful to us this way i
want to call this invoking
the logos invoking the logos
and then that will take us into neoplate
and zoom proper where we're going to
talk about
uh theoria theorgia
theologia don't be put off by this term
if you happen to be
a non-theist or an atheist and then
ultimately
dialectic into the logos
okay so there's a whole bunch of
practices here
uh we still have to go with in you know
platonism
but now we're going to do this uh
practice based on
um bizarre's work now why do i say it
overlaps with
uh stoke uh with neoplatonism uh she has
drawn this
uh from uh hashiatic prayer
hashism i think that's the way you
pronounce it
anyways it comes from heshia which is
a greek word for divine quietness divine
silence
and this is drawn from the eastern
orthodox tradition
and that is deeply meal platinum so
while i think
she is right in capturing
that this is uh overlaps with stoicism
it clearly overlaps with neoplatonism
and trying to actually divide these two
is not that helpful because
stoicism actually gets taken up into
neoplatonism neoplatonism combines
stoicism
aspects of aristotle and
aspects of plato
all together so well we'll see that of
course when we begin
the neoplatonic when we begin the
university uh when we move into the
grove
okay garden uh porch and grove
elementary school high school university
okay so let's concentrate on this
practice today
invoking the logos
so this notion of logos is deeply
important
to the stoics
and they got the notion from heraclitus
a pre-socratic philosopher
and so let's talk about what logos means
so logos means a gathering ordering
gathering things together
ordering them so that they belong
together like when you pick
a bunch of flowers you gather them
together and then you order them
together into a bouquet
or you gather together a group of
soldiers
and you organize them into a company so
that they
can fight together so the logos is a
gathering
ordering principle
in process
now that's a lot but that's because this
word logos is almost
uh it's very similar to the eastern term
dharma which means
so many things all together out all at
once
and so let me try and give you a more a
concrete example of this like
from a word that is directly derived
from this
logic okay so what are we doing with
logic
we're gathering words or thoughts
together
but not just higgledy piggledy we're
gathering them and
ordering them into propositions right
and
and then what we're doing is we are
working according to certain principles
like non-contradiction
and then what we do is that principle is
put into practice
it's put into practice or process
when we do something like deduction so
let's notice what's going to happen here
i'm going to gather words together so
they belong together
into sentences and then i'm going to
abide by the principle of
non-contradiction in the process of
deduction
all men are mortal socrates is a man
therefore socrates is mortal right i
gathered and ordered
according to principles and then i put
that into process
and so logic was taken as a
quintessential example of logos but the
problem is we have tended to forget
that logic is only an example of this
this where logos is often translated
also
as word uh so if you read the the gospel
of john
it it it gets us to try to refigure
reconfigure reinterpret the creation of
things
so genesis begins within the beginning
god created in the heavens and the earth
the gospel of john begins with in the
beginning was the word but
that's the english but what it says in
greek is in the beginning was the logos
and the logos was
with god and the logos was god and
this idea about that the logos has this
especially
intimate relationship with ultimate
reality and the ground uh the grounding
of our experience of what is sacred
or if you're more religious what is
divine
so you have to think of the logos as
trans logical
it's not just logical it's the gathering
it's not just the gathering
ordering principle in process of
thought it's the gathering ordering
principle in process
of everything everything and systems of
things
all have logos they all have this kind
of dynamic
intelligibility that makes them to be
what they are
and makes them it makes them knowable it
makes them both to be
and to be known so it's insofar as
everything has a structural functional
organization
that makes it be what it is it has a
logos
and to know it is precisely to grasp
that structural functional organization
to grasp its logos that's why we put
logos at the end of all of our studies
anthropology right
is anthropo anthropos logos
psychology is suke logos
logos of the suke logos of what it is to
be a human being
that's right if you gather all of these
threads back together you can re-weave
the tapestry
of what logos is and what it is for
the stoics so
one way to ultimately think about this
gathering this all together
is how is to think about it as the
self-presencing of everything
okay so everything it everything is
presenting
it's presenting itself as something to
you
right but there's always more right that
it can present itself as
so my here's a marker i've grasped
part of its features it's structural
functional organization
it's present to me as a marker but it
could also be present to me as
a spear etc and so you have to
think about the fact that this don't
think of this as just a static snapshot
there is an ongoing process by which
this is being
and why they when and and by which it
can be known
it's an unfolding it's a it's a it's a
dynamic
intelligibility everything is
self-presencing notice that when we want
a word
uh that talks about how we think about
things we use this idea
of representation
a representation like like like words
here's cat that's a representation of
cats or a picture of a cat
what it does is it makes the cat
presence itself to me again
right so this making sense is the act
of presencing presencing to the
mind so the idea is it was presencing in
the world
as a cat and now it's representing in
the in your mind
as the thought or concept of a cat so
you're trying to
with the logos actually combines those
two together the presencing of the cat
and the presenting of the concept of the
cat are actually
interpenetrating the one process by
which the intelligibility
the structural functional organization
of the cat is
made available to you now this sounds
fairly abstract but like i said if you
think about it
we're we're invoking this all the time
we're invoking the idea that things are
making sense to us and that that making
sense is something
we're doing but also something we're
receiving
it's ultimately something we're
participating in we're participating in
that
so from heraclitus the story's got the
idea that
all of reality all of reality is
ultimately governed
by logos so i use logos with a capital l
because what i'm talking about
you can think of here's all the
individual logo called logoi
but here's the logos right of
anthropology
uh the logos of psychology but here's
also the logos of specific objects
here's the logos of a river
and then the idea is they are all in
what and the stoics invoke this term
sympathia
they are all resonating with each other
it's very much
like layers of music and rhythm and
melody
are all in harmony with each other and
so that overarching logos is the logos
with a big
l and that's what the gospel of john
means when it says in the beginning was
the logos it means this
that that principle by which things are
and by which they are intelligible and
by which we can participate in their
self-presencing
okay so everything i was doing here
right now was logos that was logos
we could call these instead of dharmatox
it would be completely legitimate if we
were speaking it from within the western
tradition
to call them logos talks
okay now what about this notion of
invocation
it can it comes up of course in
philosophical
fellowship
this notion of invocation
okay well first of all when we're making
use of invocation where
what's it doing in us it should be
provoking
insight
and it should be evoking a sense of
emergence
something new is being realized by us
to practice this what you're basically
doing are practicing two things together
sorry three things and i'll give you an
acronym for it oh that was a mistake
okay so first there's realization
and this has that double meaning that i
was trying to convey with logos
there's the there's it's it's jane is
face it means
making sense to me and
realizing that process of presencing
being
to turn reality into a verb realizing
self-presencing but also affording and
making possible
my realization of its realization
that's the term that is being used here
your realization
and it's beyond it's not you're not just
representing things
right you're partially doing that i
i need to use a technical term here from
philosophy
but you're also instantiating so i'll
show you what i mean in concrete example
i can represent to myself
the fact that within earth's gravity i
have weight
i can think oh i know i i experience
weight
that's a representation but i actually
instantiate it
i'm actually undergoing i weight being
heavy
is self-presencing in me right now so
you have to think about this as you will
be using representations
but the point of that representation is
to get your mind to couple to
to get it deeply conformed connect
dynamically coupled to the actual
process think about the difference of
just merely representing love
with a heart and instantiating love by
kissing somebody
you're not just thinking about it you're
actually activating and
actualizing you're making an instance of
that's what this means
you're instantiating love so when you're
realizing
what you're doing here is you're not
just representing
you're actually you're actualizing
you're actualizing how something is
disclosing itself to you
you're activating it you're actualizing
it you're opening yourself
up to itself presencing so you are of
course directing your thinking towards
it
that's the one sense of realization but
you're also
letting it realize itself
in you you everything that we talk about
now is not something you think of
just think about it's something that you
are you know it
by participating in it by being it
okay so realization
and then appreciation in the three
senses of the word
i'm going to come to a deeper
understanding
like when i take a musical appreciation
class
i'm going to experience gratitude i
appreciate what you just did for me
thank you so much
the value is going to increase oh that
is appreciating in value
all three of these senses understanding
couldn't conjoin you've got
understanding
gratitude and
a sense of value increase this
creates a sense of reverence
deep understanding that is coupled to
deep gratitude
that is coupled to a deep sense of the
emergence of new value new meaning
new connectedness
and then participation
right so this is knowing
by being i've already talked about this
if you do these other ones that leads
into this you know it by being it
you are at one with it you are enjoying
it
remember the whole point of stoicism
is this kind of joy where you realize
and appreciate and participate in the
depths of the flow of nature and that
flow of nature also comes from
heraclitus
because heraclitus thought that the flow
of nature
is a logos so this gives you an acronym
by the way
rap right
i want you to rap as a verb the logos
because rap is this combination of music
and speech
imagine if you take everything in music
everything in speech
and put them together that's the state
you have to be in
to invoke the logos you invoke it the
way you invoke
music the way you appreciate it and
participate in it but you're also
speaking out you're making
sense okay
i'm going to take you through this
exercise now
i'll first of all explain it on the
board and then we'll go back and we'll
sit
and we will go through it together i'll
talk you through
this practice
okay so let's use what she talks about
uh
sorry she says first sitting like a
mountain
this is number one and this is the greek
hexis she doesn't translate it for you
which is
odd but this means state or
trait or habit this is you
realizing how you inhabit your mind and
body
you inhabit your mind and body
and so what you're trying to get here is
what we're going through here is we're
going through layers of the logos
here you're picking up on the stability
the self-perpetuation of self-presencing
there's a stability to things they're
not just flipping in and out of
existence
there's a stability to them the
stability of self uh perpetuation
think about how logic stabilizes your
thoughts
okay and then we're going to move to
sitting like a poppy
i don't know why poppy particular or
just like a flower
okay so this is the greek word phusis
it's where we get physics from
but fuses doesn't mean what we now mean
by physical fuses me and this is why
she's using the flower fosis means
blooming forth springing forth from
itself it has to do
more with self-organized emergence and
so what you're picking up
on now is the vitality of everything how
everything
is there's a logos to it but that logos
is making everything emerge
all the atoms of this are being right
gathered together
ordered together so that this marker
emerges
everything it has that kind of vitality
to it
the vitality of
self-organization
the third one is
there's a there's an ascent here as you
can see
sitting like an ocean
here what you're trying to pick up on i
think she's a little bit
uh oh i wanted to um
this is has to do uh with
hexis this has to do as i said with
fuses
and this has to do with suitcase where
we get the word psyche from
um it's she she writes it this way
the greek is in between our y and our u
so that's why you see these double
uh writings here
what we're talking about is an ocean now
think about the ways of an ocean
and you've got your waves of your breath
to help you right and think about prajna
so when you're taking the in-breath the
moreness right
they're all of the possibilities all of
the relations
and then so the mystery of the mornis
and then it comes into the shining
suchness the particular thing
so this is how everything is
self-determining so we've got how
everything is
self-perpetuating texas how everything
is self-organizing that vitality of
self-organization
and now we have how everything is
intelligible because it's
it's self-determining this is a way of
talking about this from the guy
a scholar named pearl look at this word
it's great so when you're trying to
determine what something is
you're trying to write make sense about
figure it's order
but when you're determined you're also
right setting yourself
onto something and people talk about
determinism
that means that everything is ordered in
the universe
everything is a self-determining thing
everything spinoza talked about this
like as canatus
so everything is self-perpetuating
and you're saying these all are similar
that's the point they're all different
aspects they're all layers of the logos
everything is gathering together right
ordering
so that it has a stability it has a
vitality
and it has an intelligibility it is you
can determine what it is
and it is determined to be what it is
and then finally sitting like a sage
back to internalizing the sage and the
part of this
is noose this comes from the greek word
noin which means
to uh to notice but not
through discursive thought it means to
notice to have a a
an integrative comprehensive insight
that sizes things
up and gets you to put you in contact
with their logos
and here what are we trying to pick up
on
here we're trying to pick up on
how everything has an aspect of
self-transcendence to it
everything is much more than it seems to
be
and everything is much more than we
think it
to be
notice what we're doing is we're
intensifying the self-presencing
so she says when we're sitting like a
mountain we want to sense the weight
of presence that stability
and then when we're sitting like a puppy
it's like a a flower turning towards the
sun we want to sense the energy
the weight of self-presencing
the energy of self-presencing
this is like the music the rhythm the
measure
of self-presencing and this is the
source
sensing the source astending reaching in
ineffability towards the source
because in the beginning it's not only
right in the beginning
was the logos and the logos was with god
but somehow the logos also
is god towards the source
so this gives us our grounding right
we're picking up on our grounding
this gives us a sense on how things are
emerging this gives us the things on how
things are ordered how they're
determined
and this gives us uh a sense of how
things are ascending
how they are pointing back to
the the ineffable inexhaustible source
of it all
all right so the thing we're gonna do
now is we're going to go i'm going to go
back
we're going to switch camera again i'm
going to sit and i'm going to just take
you through this
practice
okay so we're switching the camera now
all right so let's take a moment of
silence try to do this as briefly as you
can but i want you to find your core
four
i want you to center find your center
find your route find your flow
very important for this practice and
find your focus
so we'll take a moment of silence and
then i will basically talk you walk you
through
the practice so a moment is a couple
moments of silence
bring your attention to how you are
rooted how you are
sitting like a mountain although still
alert as a warrior
invoke the stability within you
the way you're inhabiting your mind and
body
is premised on the fact that there's a
stability a self-perpetuation of your
body and your mind
that you participate in you don't make
it you participate in it
sense that layer of the logos
the way there's a stability that allows
you to inhabit
your mind and your body
sense the weight of the self-presencing
of reality
now sense that also outside of you
resonate with it there's a stability to
things that allows you to inhabit the
world
the stability in the flow that's the
logos
it's the logos without and it
corresponds and is at one
with the logos within
now sitting like a poppy like a flower
feel the vitality within you the life
within you
the self-organizing flow of life that
vitality
the energy of self-presencing the energy
of the logos
feel it as continuous with the stability
now sense that vitality outside of you
everything is self-organizing energy
everything has energy flowing through it
the vitality within and the vitality
without
sense the vitality at one the logos
within and out
that energy of self-presencing
stability within and without
energy within and without
now since the music
everything about you is making sense
in a felt way also in a conceptual way
it's like music
it's making sense it's self-determining
you can determine
everything is structured to be the way
it is but to be knowable
in the way that it is
sense that music within the
intelligibility of the logos
that music is continuous with the energy
the vitality and the stability the
weight
sense the intelligibility without
everything is in process
but not as chaos it makes sense
it's intelligible
you can connect to it you can appreciate
it
the music within and the music without
our one music
the music of the logos
the energy of the logos
the weight of the logos
sitting like an ocean
flowing in and out
that rhythm that pattern that music that
we've been talking about
pick up on it
it's hitting like an ocean the waves of
being
warn us into suchness suchness and
awareness
the weight of the logos
the energy of the logos the music of the
logos
now sitting like a sage
the source of this all the source of all
these layers
of logos of the weight of
self-presencing
the energy of self-presencing the
intelligibility of self-presencing the
music
there's an eternal source of it all
from which it emanates and to which it
always returns
logos was with god and the logos was god
as we gathered them together sitting
like a mountain
the weight of self-presencing
sitting like a poppy the energy of
self-presencing
sitting like an ocean the music
the self-determination the waves of
being
of self-presencing
sitting like a sage
everything pointing towards the source
of it all
the ineffable source
okay slowly come out of your practice
and we have time
we're going to take a few a couple of
questions
uh we're just waiting for the first
question to come up
um this is from aleph one two three you
this goes back to previous lesson you
said
uh not start with primaritario as you
might go too deep and struggle with
fatality do you have any suggestions
as what what on one what to do if one
thinks one has
things figured out but lack this virtue
of respect
um if you think you have
things figured out it is perhaps a good
chance there or
sorry a good time uh to take up
pre-meditation
the stoics were always reminding us of
the the moreness
and there's sort of a positive and
negative sense of the mourners
there's a there's a happy sense of
interconnectedness there's so
much more and that should induce awe
in the sense of awesome and that will
help
to get you out of the sense that you
figured it out
but then there's the sense of right
there's so much more than me
in a sense of impermanence
everything will pass away and of course
the buddhist notion is that impermanence
and interdependence are completely
identical
in a non-logical way with each other the
stoics are saying something very similar
so there's so much more i'm so connected
ah awesome
i'm so much there's so much more
everything
is passing away arising and passing away
the waves of
being arising and passing away the music
of being the ocean of being
and that's the ocean can be not only
awesome
the ocean can be awful
take up that practice as a way of
remembering in the sense of in invoking
and internalizing
there's so much more of you do both if
you do just one
you inflate and you think yourself a god
if you do just other you fall into
despair and think of yourself as nothing
more than a passing insect
the two together optimal grip
tonos
manual post i've been struggling with
good methods of gathering feedback on
practices
any suggestion uh so if you mean from
yourself or from others
um so from others you the standard
practices you want to do
is you want to try and create a
questionnaire and then you want to make
sure
that the questionnaire is reliably
giving you the kind of information
that gives you uh both what you're doing
right
and what you're doing wrong and so you
often have to
re keep reconfiguring keep rewriting the
questionnaire
until you get a set of questions it
seems to be reliably predictive
of how well people are doing so once
you've run the test
on people like to to get it then what
you do is you turn it around
you don't ask people where they're at in
their practice you ask them these
questions you get
feedback from from answers to the
question and then you try to predict
how they're doing in their practice when
you
when your questionnaire accurately can
predict
how they're doing with their own
self-assessment and any
external measures remember what's more
important is transformations in their
life
then your questionnaire is considered to
have a kind of validity to it
and then you can start using it you can
of course try the same thing with
yourself
it's a little bit more difficult uh but
the thing might be do to try and work
this out with other people and then
apply it uh to yourself
manual posts i tend to rotate my head in
the direction i'm putting my awareness
in meditation
i think this results in me losing my
posture over time any suggestions
um is there oh yeah that this is
something that people fall into
is there a way of you like perhaps when
you're not even meditating
sit and practice moving your attention
around
without altering your eyes or your head
you can do this by the way
it's called a covert shift of attention
it's well established and you can get
better out of practice
so practice covert shifting of attention
while you're just sitting not you're not
meditating just sitting looking out in
your room
practice and then train yourself and
teach yourself
you know confidence faith in yourself
confidence
having faith in yourself that you can
shift your attention
without having to actually enact even
moving your eyes
or even more so moving your head so
practice that a lot until you get to
that ability
where you know in practice what it is to
exercise covert shifts of attention
mark the feb i find this concept of all
bad acts being assigned to ignorance to
be in conflict with the concept of
justice
any thoughts on how to resolve this does
neoplaton doesn't fix this
i find this concept of all bad acts
being assigned to ignorance be in
conflict with the concept
so um so i think mark is talking about
the stoic idea which actually comes from
plato um
that nobody knowingly commits um evil
um and so you have to mark if you
perhaps understood
ignorance in a much more comprehensive
sense
of of illusion and self-deception
and so the basic idea here is people
do what is wrong because they
misapprehend it
they misconstrue it as something good
and then so that sense the ignorance is
um
not sort of a lack of basic knowledge
it's a lack of a correct understanding
that's why
right understanding is part of the
eightfold path without a right
understanding uh people fall into
self-deception and then the idea is
it's ultimately self-deceptive behavior
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
then that's this is analogous in some
ways to karma that's a pattern
that you know promulgates out from you
other people catch it
so your self-destructiveness also
becomes other destructiveness
and that's why it is uh considered the
source of bad acts
um so perhaps what was concerning you
about justice is
that justice requires a sense of
responsibility
um but i don't think that is being
violated here because the
the the the central platonic claim is
you the these people are failing living
to failing and this is the
core stoicism they're failing to live up
to the the deepest most important
part of responsibility that which is
actually most
in your control which is your ability to
overcome
self-deception to see things as they are
to have
insight and wisdom so
there's a sense in which people are
failing to live up to
the fundamental responsibility to
themselves because that fundamental
responsibility to yourself
the cultivation of wisdom is what is
needed to overcome self-deception
and prevent doing um immoral or unjust
acts
and so and plato also turns it the other
way before you consider
doing anything evil or bad towards other
people
you have to first partially destroy
yourself
because you have to give in or you have
to avoid or give in
to self-deception which is ultimately
self-destructive so the person
this sounds strange and it may wrankle
us a little bit but plato argues that
the person that does evil
is actually even more harmed than any
harm they do
to each other because the idea is to do
that to another person
requires tremendous self-deception
and self-destructive harm so you're
ultimately self-harming
and then the idea is nobody would
willingly self-harm
now there are again when people do
self-harm they cut themselves but
they're diluted that that will actually
alleviate their psychological pain
and that cut and physical pain is the
best way of of ameliorating
uh the psychological pain which is which
is
incorrect um so
i think i think that would answer your
question mark
uh about this um
it's it's a very i this is a really
um this has always been a famously
challenging
idea from both stoicism and platonism
and therefore also neoplatonism
uh and augustine for example augustine
famously rejected it one of the
distinctions between christianity
um and neo-platonism although he
integrated the two together or between
christianity and stoicism
is uh augustine thought that people were
actually capable of doing evil for its
own sake that they
were always licking the earth or
scratching
the open sore of lust that sort of thing
that's one of the big division points
and it's hard to find
evidence for this augustine said he did
something
just because it was wrong and i mean i
i take i'm to be sincere but when you
look at his situation
that love of destructiveness
um it seems to be part of a pattern of
reciprocal narrowing on his part
and so i don't
think that that's the correct correct
way
to put it i ultimately don't agree uh
with that notion
of augustine i think a better way of
interpreting
original sin that's his notion it's not
like a disease within us
but more like the buddhist notion that
the very processes that make us adaptive
are the processes that make us
vulnerable uh to self-deception
so i i prefer thinking that in terms of
dukkha
rather than original sin random name
how should one go about learning all of
these greek words are there books
specific to this
or other online resources yes there's
books you can get
on that translate i'll put it in the
description
they give you a translation of greek
philosophical terms there's greek
philosophical term dictionaries
you can purchase you can also look the
terms up online
so and most of them are given a
definition
i is there a glossary in mcclellan there
might be
i'll have to double check
the deborah wagstaff the intelligent
just waiting for the question to come up
the intelligibility the music the
determinant determinism in everyone the
music we're all making together
that everything and everyone has we are
not making it we are participating in it
together
that's exactly right that's exactly
right
that's exactly right
that's exactly correct so
notice that this is satie
what we're doing is in in the way we're
wrapping
right the logos invoking it we're doing
a deep profound kind of remembering
that reconnects us it re-grounds us
it causes us to participate in the
emergence
it gives us right it helps us to
recognize
to recognize to make sense again that's
what recognize literally means
to recognize to make sense again and
ultimately to participate to be
at one with it a profound sense of
integration
and unity okay
everyone that's it uh for today
oh i'll take one more question it just
came up random name i've been reading
spinoza's collective works which parts
would you say
one should pay extra attention to and
which parts are easily misunderstood
is there an email i can reach out to
i'll talk to omar about
the potential email um which parts you
should pay extra attention to
um
depends i mean the ethics i think is the
part that ultimately
on the correction or the improvement of
the understanding is very important
um the ethics is the central text um
it's it's too easy to misinterpret what
spinoza is doing as a
theory but it's not called a theory it's
called the ethics
the most important misunderstanding and
misapprehension people of spinoza
is they read it and think what they're
doing is gathering a theory
the theory is is totally in service of
theoria
you're supposed to go to a place where
you're not believing the theory
you're seeing reality the way spinoza
did
scancia intuitiva that all at once
understanding of how everything fits
together all these layers of logos
interpenetrate
and mutually constrain and afford and
are at one with each other
not in the homogenous sense
but in this dynamic coupled sense
so i want to thank everyone for joining
i want to thank amara and jason
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video follow me on
twitter
for any updates about these streams
invite others who might
benefit by sharing this series please
join the discord server
uh to engage in a lot of these practice
and join a community
there's a link in the description uh
we're doing this every saturday morning
at
uh 10 a.m eastern time we will have a
general q a we were supposed to do it
uh yesterday a third friday uh but we're
postponing it
my health was not has not been good the
past couple of days and so we're
postponing it to
uh next friday and please remember if
you can to send me a clip of yourself no
more
than 10 seconds for the compilation
video send it to amar
john verveicky.com
so please remember
continuity of practice is more important
than quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to a standard of
harsh perfectionism but virtuous
friendship
for there is no friend better
than your own mind and body be lamps
unto yourselves
and to each other take good care
everyone see you next saturday
bye bye
you